Finding Aid for Frank R. Kennedy Papers
Bentley Historical Library
Frank R. Kennedy Papers
1936-1999
1960-1979
Bentley Historical Library
Kennedy, Frank R., 1914-
9961 Aa 2
28 linear feet
Professor of bankruptcy law at the University of Michigan Law School and helped to formulate modern bankruptcy law. Member of the National Bankruptcy Conference, the Advisory Committee on Bankruptcy Rules, and the Commission on Bankruptcy Laws. Participated in the formulation of the Bankruptcy Reform Act of 1978; correspondence, reports, minutes, articles, and collected research, 1960-1979, documenting his membership in bankruptcy law and his work on committees drafting bankruptcy law proposals.
The collection was donated by Frank R. Kennedy (Donor 8849 ) in March 1999.
The collection is open for research.
Frank Robert Kennedy, a distinguished legal scholar on the subject of bankruptcy law, made a lifetime of contributions to the scholarship of bankruptcy law in the United States, and to the formation of bankruptcy law and procedures. His work in the field of bankruptcy over fifty years helped shape bankruptcy law and what was to become the Bankruptcy Reform Act of 1978 through his involvement in many of the conferences and committees that drafted the legislation for congressional debate. He was a professor of bankruptcy law at the University of Iowa and at the University of Michigan. He taught bankruptcy law and related subjects at the University of Michigan from 1961 to 1984.
Kennedy was born July 27, 1914, in Strafford, Missouri. He attended Southwest Missouri State University from 1931 to 1935 and received an A.B. and a teaching license. He received his law degree from Washington University School of Law, attending from 1936 to 1939. While at Washington University, he was first in his class all three years and was a member of the law review. It was while at Washington University that he took courses in secured transactions and debtor's estates. It was as a result of these classes that he decided to pursue his interests in bankruptcy and corporate reorganization. After completing his law degree, he received the Sterling Fellowship at Yale University Law School which allowed him to pursue a Juris Scientia Doctor (J.S.D), an advanced law degree. This was common practice at that time for those lawyers who wanted to become law professors. While at Yale, he was a protégé of J.W. Moore, a leading academician on Chapter X reorganization, and helped him revise Collier on Bankruptcy. Professor Moore also helped him gain membership to the National Bankruptcy Conference.
World War II interrupted Kennedy's work on his J.S.D. thesis. He spent the war (1943-1946) in the Navy working as a personnel officer at the Naval Air Station, Quonset Point, Rhode Island. He became a law professor at the University of Iowa in 1940 and continued to work on his J.S.D. thesis which he successfully completed in 1953. He taught at the University of Iowa from 1940 to 1942 and 1946 to 1960. His primary subjects of instruction were: bankruptcy, secured transactions, creditor's rights, restitution, trade regulation, federal jurisdiction, and constitutional law.
In addition to his academic career, he participated in the bankruptcy law profession as a member of committees and conferences whose mission it was to examine, supervise, and revise the bankruptcy laws and procedural bankruptcy rules of the United States. In this role, he has served as a member of the National Bankruptcy Conference (NBC) since 1947. The purpose of the NBC is to study bankruptcy case administration and develop needed amendments when requested by the United States House and Senate Judiciary Committees. As a member of the NBC he has acted as chairman of the Drafting Committee and member of the executive committee, 1959 and as secretary, 1981-1990. In 1959 he was also invited to become the reporter for the first Advisory Committee on Bankruptcy Rules of the Judicial Conference of the United States (ACBR), of which he was a member from 1960 to 1976. The ACBR was formed to draft rules of procedure for bankruptcy courts. This included drafting a statute that authorized the Supreme Court to promulgate procedural rules even if they conflicted with the existing Bankruptcy Act, an unusual grant of powers considering the separation of powers under the Constitution. This authority was later removed by the Bankruptcy Reform Act of 1978. Professor Kennedy was appointed executive director of the Commission on Bankruptcy Laws (CBL) in 1970. The CBL was authorized by Congress to study the current bankruptcy laws and process. The CBL grew out of a long-standing issue in the legal community regarding the status of bankruptcy courts and whether the bankruptcy process should be an administrative rather than a judicial procedure. It held hearings all over the country regarding issues in bankruptcy law. In 1973, the CBL produced bankruptcy legislation to propose to Congress. Although the legislation did not pass that year, it helped to lay the foundation for the Bankruptcy Reform Act of 1978.
Professor Kennedy's relationship with the University of Michigan began in 1958 when he was a visiting professor. The university was looking for a professor in bankruptcy and reorganization after the death of professor Edgar Durfee, and Michigan persuaded him to return. He returned as a permanent professor in 1961, and remained at the university until 1984 when he was given emeritus status. He came to Michigan because of the opportunity to dedicate more of his teaching and scholarly time to bankruptcy-related issues. While at Michigan he taught creditor's rights, bankruptcy, reorganization, secured transactions, and consumer credit. He received the Distinguished Faculty Achievement award in 1971. He was named the Thomas M. Cooley Professor of Law in 1979. Over time he has contributed prodigious scholarship to the field of bankruptcy law by having almost 170 articles published in law reviews or contributed to legal treatises. In 1997 he was recognized for fifty years of membership in the Association of American University Professors.
He also served as Of Counsel to Sidley & Austin in Chicago, IL from 1983 to 1994. His civic involvement includes membership in the Ann Arbor Rotary Club where he served as president from 1979 to 1980.
The Frank R. Kennedy papers are composed primarily of the work resulting from his membership in the Advisory Committee on Bankruptcy Rules of the Judicial Conference of the United States (ACBR), the National Bankruptcy Conference (NBC), and the Commission on Bankruptcy Laws (CBL). In addition the collection contains over sixty years of professional correspondence documenting the scholarly and professional work of Professor Kennedy in the field of bankruptcy law. The entire collection spans 1936 to 1999 with the bulk of the collection falling between 1960 and 1979. The collection is divided into ten major series: Advisory Committee on Bankruptcy Rules, Bankruptcy Reform Act, Biographical Information, Commission on the Bankruptcy Laws of the United States, General Correspondence, National Bankruptcy Conference, Other Organizational Affiliations, Teaching, Uniform Fraudulent Transfer Act, and Writings and Research.
Bankruptcy -- Law and legislation -- United States.; Bankruptcy -- United States.; Law -- Study and teaching.; Kennedy, Frank R., 1914-; University of Michigan -- Law School.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; Countryman, Vern.; King, Lawrence.; MacLachlan, James Angell, 1891-1967.; Horsky, Charles Antone.; Durfee, Edgar Noble, 1882-1952.
- Advisory Committee on Bankruptcy Rules
  The first series, Advisory Committee on Bankruptcy Rules, (2 linear feet) relates to his work as reporter for the committee and his sixteen-year membership from 1960 to 1976. The subseries of correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order in each folder. The correspondence includes exchanges with members of Congress and copies of the laws resulting from the committee's discussion, as well as minutes of ACBR meetings. Correspondents include Lawrence King of New York University and Vern Countryman of Harvard University. The Official Forms subseries contains correspondence, drafts, revisions and ballots relating to the revision of particular legal forms used in bankruptcy. The topical subseries is collected background materials used for developing particular general orders and official forms. The materials in this subseries include: research, reports, minutes, correspondence, ballots, and memoranda.
  - Correspondence re: Substantive Matters
    - February-December 1960, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - January-December 1961, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - January-August 1962 (Box 1)
    - September 1962-November 1963, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - December 1963-October 1964, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - November 1964-March 1966, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - May 1966-1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Official Forms
    - 1 and Schedules, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 2 and 3 (Box 2)
    - 4 and 5 (Box 2)
    - 6-14 (Box 2)
    - 17 (Box 2)
    - 18-25 (Box 2)
    - 27-39 (Box 2)
    - 40-51 (Box 2)
    - 52-62 (Box 2)
  - Topical, 1953-1970
    - Administration (Box 2)
    - Adversary proceedings (Box 2)
    - After-acquired property (Box 2)
    - Allowances (Box 2)
    - Bautista's drafts of Rules (Box 2)
    - Chapter X, XI, and XII (Box 2)
    - Chapter XIII (Box 2)
    - Costs of bankruptcy administration (Box 2)
    - Disqualification of referees (Box 2)
    - Filing of claims by bankrupt or debtor (Box 2)
    - Final meeting: Order and notice (Box 2)
    - General Order 55 (Box 2)
    - General Provisions (Box 2)
    - Injunctions and stays (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous general orders and forms (Box 2)
    - Multiple notice forms (Box 2)
    - Notice of non-disclosure (Box 2)
    - Official forms (Box 2)
    - Official receivers and trustees (Box 2)
    - Petition and proceedings to adjudication (Box 2)
    - Public Law 88-623 (Box 3)
    - Review of Official Forms (Box 3)
    - Signing of papers and verifications (Box 3)
    - Unification of civil and admiralty rules (Box 3)
- Bankruptcy Reform Act
  The second series, Bankruptcy Reform Act, (1 linear foot) contains materials related to various pieces of proposed legislation in the House and the Senate in the 1960s and 1970s which ultimately resulted in the Bankruptcy Reform Act of 1978. The materials include a draft Bankruptcy Act annotated by Vern Countryman, noted scholar in bankruptcy law at Harvard Law School and member of the NBC and ACBR. The series also includes annotated bills and the accompanying testimony on the legislation. The testimony includes statements from Professor Kennedy as well as other bankruptcy law professionals and interested parties.
  - Bibliography, 1975-1981 (Box 3)
  - Draft Bankruptcy Act, annotated, 1973 (Box 3)
  - House Legislation
    - HR 31, 1973 (Box 3)
    - HR 235/236, 1975 (Box 3)
    - HR 8200, 1976-1978; 5 folders (Box 3)
    - HR 9191, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Index to Hearings on Bankruptcy Legislation (Box 3)
  - Senate Legislation
    - S 2266, 1977-1979; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - S 2565 (Box 4)
- Biographical Information
  The third series, Biographical Information, (1 linear foot) includes a bibliography of Professor Kennedy's scholarly work, and general biographical materials which include an oral history completed in 1994. The series also includes personal recollections of his family's history. His academic life is best represented in papers from his studies at Washington University. These papers include exams and briefs written during his final year in law school. The remainder of the series includes papers relating to alumni activities and fundraising activities for institutions with which he was involved.
  - Bibliography (Box 4)
  - General Biographical Materials (Box 4)
  - Personal Recollections (Box 4)
  - Southwest Missouri State University (Box 4)
  - Springfield Public Schools Foundation (Box 4)
  - University of Iowa (Box 4)
  - Washington University School of Law, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Yale Law School Fund (Box 4)
- Commission on the Bankruptcy Laws of the United States
  The fourth series, Commission on the Bankruptcy Laws of the United States, (3 linear feet) relates to his work as the first Executive Director of the Commission and the organization's role to propose a comprehensive new bankruptcy code. The materials include transcripts from the hearings held nationally regarding the reform of the bankruptcy law. The correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order; included in the correspondence are briefs, memos, and CBL minutes with attachments. Please note that the attachments are arranged by topic for the purposes of the meeting and not in reverse chronological order. There is also a portion of correspondence spanning 1974-1978 which occurred after the dissolution of the Commission and relate to the conclusion of the business of the Commission.
  - Correspondence
    - July 1970-July 1971 (Box 4)
    - September 1971-December 1971, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - January 1972-October 1972, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - November-December 1972, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - January-February 1973, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - March-April 1973, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - May-June 1973, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - April-December 1974, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - January-December 1975, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 6)
  - Hearings
    - Transcripts
      - March 1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - May 1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - October 1972 (Box 6)
      - November 1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Written Statements
      - N.d (Box 6)
      - March 1972 (Box 6)
      - May 1972 (Box 6)
  - Reports
    - Commission on Bankruptcy Laws Report, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Rand Report, 1973 (Box 7)
- General Correspondence
  The fifth series, General Correspondence, (3 linear feet) contains sixty-three years worth of correspondence arranged in chronological order by year and then in alphabetical order by the last name of the correspondent. The correspondence is mixed personal and professional, with the bulk of the materials being professional correspondence. Noted correspondents include Vern Countryman and Carl Frebolin, a prominent referee in bankruptcy.
  - 1936-1947, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - 1948 (Box 7)
  - 1949 (Box 7)
  - 1950 (Box 7)
  - 1951 (Box 7)
  - 1952 (Box 7)
  - 1953, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1954, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1955 (Box 7)
  - 1956, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1957 (Box 7)
  - 1958 (Box 7)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 7)
  - 1961 (Box 7)
  - 1962, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1963, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1964, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1965, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - 1966, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - 1967, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1968, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1969, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1970, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1971 (Box 8)
  - 1972 (Box 8)
  - 1973 (Box 8)
  - 1974, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1975, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1976 (Box 8)
  - 1977 (Box 8)
  - 1978 (Box 8)
  - 1979, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - 1980, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1981, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1982, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1983, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1984 (Box 9)
  - 1985, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1986 (Box 9)
  - 1987, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1988 (Box 9)
  - 1989 (Box 9)
  - 1990 (Box 9)
  - 1991 (Box 9)
  - 1992 (Box 9)
  - 1993 (Box 9)
  - 1994 (Box 9)
  - 1995 (Box 9)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 9)
  - 1998, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1999 (Box 9)
- National Bankruptcy Conference
  The sixth series, National Bankruptcy Conference, (7 linear feet) represents his 40-year membership in the Conference, and his work as chairman of the Drafting Committee. The first subseries tracks the history of the NBC prior to Kennedy's membership in papers from James MacLachlan, one of the first members of the NBC during the period which resulted in the Chandler Act. The Chandler Act was the first major bankruptcy legislation in the United States. This subseries consists of correspondence arranged in reverse chronological order. Correspondents included in this subseries are Henry Cabot Lodge, as well as other conferees, John Gerdes, Paul King, Watson Adair, Jacob Weinstein, Charles T. Adams, and W. Randolph Montgomery. The second subseries covers the period of Professor Kennedy's membership in the NBC and span 1954-1998. The subseries consists of annual meeting materials, correspondence, Drafting Committee materials and topical files. The annual meeting materials spans 1954-1998 with the bulk of the meetings represented from 1956 to 1979. In some cases the material covers two meetings held in the same year. The collection contains only a few examples of the summaries of proceedings that were produced following the meetings. The materials collected from the annual meetings include the reports of subcommittees, annotated agendas, executive committee papers, as well as some correspondence specifically related to the annual meetings. The correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order by the last name of the correspondent. Correspondents in this series include Vern Countryman and Charles Horsky. The Drafting Committee materials consist of reports, drafts and correspondence. The drafts and the correspondence are arranged in reverse chronological order. In the case of the correspondence, if a specific section of the Act is referenced in the letter it is noted in the upper right-hand corner of the letter. Members of this committee included Vern Countryman, professor of law at Harvard, and Lawrence King, law professor at New York University. The topical files include correspondence and reports in reverse chronological order. Topics include drafts of approved revisions of amendments to the Bankruptcy Act, American Bar Association committees, special meetings of the NBC, and the materials of special NBC committees.
  - 1932-1939
    - MacLachlan Correspondence
      - N.d (Box 10)
      - 1932-1933 (Box 10)
      - 1937-January 1938 (Box 10)
      - February-October 1938, 4 folders (Box 10)
      - November 1938-January 1939 (Box 10)
  - 1954-1998
    - Annual Meeting
      - 1954 (Box 10)
      - January 1956 (Box 10)
      - November 1956 (Box 10)
      - 1957 (Box 10)
      - 1958 (Box 10)
      - 1959 (Box 10)
      - 1960 (Box 10)
      - 1961 (Box 10)
      - 1962 (Box 10)
      - 1963 (Box 10)
      - 1964 (Box 10)
      - 1965 (Box 10)
      - 1966 (Box 10)
      - 1967 (Box 10)
      - 1968, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1969 (Box 11)
      - 1970, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1971 (Box 11)
      - 1972 (Box 11)
      - 1973 (Box 11)
      - 1974, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - 1975, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1976, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1977, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1979 (Box 12)
      - 1980 (Box 12)
      - 1981 (Box 12)
      - 1982 (Box 12)
      - 1983 (Box 12)
      - February 1984 (Box 12)
      - October 1984 (Box 12)
      - 1997
        - Committee Reports, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - February 1998, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - December 1998, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Correspondence
      - B (Box 12)
      - C (Box 12)
      - Congressional correspondence (Box 12)
      - Coogan, Peter (Box 12)
      - Countryman, Vern, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - D, E, F (Box 12)
      - G, H, I, J (Box 13)
      - Horsky, Charles (Box 13)
      - K (Box 13)
      - Knox, William (Box 13)
      - L, M, N (Box 13)
      - Levin/Klee (Box 13)
      - MacLachlan, James (Box 13)
      - O, P, Q (Box 13)
      - Plumb, William T., Jr. (Box 13)
      - R (Box 13)
      - Rochelle, William (Box 13)
      - S (Box 13)
      - Seligson, Charles (Box 13)
      - Smith, Gerald K (Box 13)
      - T (Box 13)
      - U-V (Box 13)
      - W, X, Y, Z (Box 13)
    - Drafting Committee
      - 1957 (Box 13)
      - 1958 (Box 13)
      - 1959, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - 1960, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - 1961, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - 1962
        - January-May, 2 folders (Box 13)
        - June-December, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - 1963, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - 1964, 5 folders (Box 14)
      - 1965, 4 folders (Box 14)
      - 1966, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - 1967, 4 folders (Box 14)
      - 1968, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - 1969, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - 1970-1972 (Box 15)
      - 1975 (Box 15)
      - 1997 (Box 15)
    - Topical
      - ABA Commercial Bankruptcy Committee (Box 15)
      - ABA Federal Regulation of Securities Committee (Box 15)
      - ABA Fidelity and Surety Committee (Box 15)
      - Approved Amendments of Revisions to the Bankruptcy Act, 10 folders (Box 15)
      - Committee on Coordination of the Bankruptcy Act and the UCC, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Committee on Reorganization Plans and Securities Problems (Box 15)
      - Draft Bankruptcy Legislation, 1998 (Box 15)
      - Educational Session on Consumer Bankruptcy (Box 15)
      - Harvard Meeting, 1978 (Box 15)
      - H.R. 3150 Conference Report, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - H.R. 3150 Analysis and Reports, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Legislative Updates on Bankruptcy Reform (Box 16)
      - Meeting of NBC and Bankruptcy Judges, 1955 (Box 16)
      - Membership Committee, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Partnerships and Bankruptcy, 1997; 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Report on the Bankruptcy Act and Community Property (Box 16)
      - Reports and Notes, 1974; 1976; 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Revision of R.S. 3466, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Special Committee on Establishment of a Separate Court of Bankruptcy, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Summaries of Proceedings of Annual Meetings
      - 1948 (Box 28)
      - 1951 (Box 28)
      - 1953 (Box 28)
      - 1954 (Box 28)
      - 1956 (Box 28)
        (January)
      - 1956 (Box 28)
        (November)
      - 1957 (Box 28)
      - 1958 (Box 28)
      - 1959 (Box 28)
      - 1960 (Box 28)
      - 1961 (Box 28)
      - 1962 (Box 28)
      - 1962 (Box 28)
        (Transcript, Volume 1)
      - 1962 (Box 28)
        (Transcript, Volume 2)
      - 1963 (Box 28)
      - 1963 (Box 28)
      - 1963 (Box 28)
      - 1964 (Box 28)
      - 1965 (Box 28)
      - 1966 (Box 28)
      - 1967 (Box 28)
      - 1968 (Box 28)
      - 1969 (Box 28)
      - 1970 (Box 28)
      - 1972-1974 (Box 28)
      - 1975, 1976; 1977; 1979 (Box 28)
      - 1980-1984 (Box 28)
- Other Organizational Affiliations
  The seventh series, Other Organizational Affiliations, (.5 linear feet) contains materials from the many organizations where Professor Kennedy held membership. Many of the organizations represented are professional in nature, the Association of American Law Schools and the American Association of University Professors. Other organizations relate to law and bankruptcy -- the American Bar Association (ABA), the American Law Institute (ALI), American College of Bankruptcy, and Order of the Coif. The last organization listed is a community organization, Rotary.